<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Santiago Muñoz Arbeláez</title>
    <description>PhD en Historia, Yale University</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>2019-04-14</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2019 21:00:36 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.7.4</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Libro digital, Mapeando Colombia</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;mapeando-colombia-la-construcción-del-territorio&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://bibliotecanacional.gov.co/es-co/colecciones/biblioteca-digital/mapeando/Paginas/capitulouno.html&quot;&gt;Mapeando Colombia: la construcción del territorio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;La Biblioteca Nacional de Colombia está publicando un libro digital dirigido a una audiencia amplia que examina la historia de Colombia a través de sus mapas, tocando temas diversos desde la cartografía indígena y la expansión atlántica hasta la cartografía satelital de los siglos XX y XXI. Se trata de un libro por entregas del que se va publicando un capítulo mensualmente. Pueden consultar el libro acá: &lt;a href=&quot;http://bibliotecanacional.gov.co/es-co/colecciones/biblioteca-digital/mapeando/Paginas/capitulouno.html&quot;&gt;http://bibliotecanacional.gov.co/es-co/colecciones/biblioteca-digital/mapeando/Paginas/capitulouno.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>2019-04-14</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/2018-04/libro-digital-mapeando-colombia</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/2018-04/libro-digital-mapeando-colombia</guid>
        
        
        <category>Noticias</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Neogranadina se alía con el MAP</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;La Fundación Histórica Neogranadina se alía con el Medici Archive Project con el objetivo de desarrollar e implementar la plataforma digital más avanzada para la visualización y consulta en línea de los archivos históricos colombianos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Puede encontrar más información en la &lt;a href=&quot;https://neogranadina.org&quot;&gt;página de la fundación&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>2019-04-14</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/2016-05/neogranadina-map</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/2016-05/neogranadina-map</guid>
        
        
        <category>Noticias</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Material Methodologies in Latin American &amp; Iberian Studies</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/Columbia.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Material Methodologis&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;material-methodologies-in-latin-american--iberian-studies&quot;&gt;Material Methodologies in Latin American &amp;amp; Iberian Studies&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;one-day-symposium-october-17-2015&quot;&gt;One-Day Symposium, October 17, 2015&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;host-department-of-latin-american--iberian-cultures-columbia-university&quot;&gt;Host: Department of Latin American &amp;amp; Iberian Cultures, Columbia University&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;sponsor-the-andrew-w-mellon-fellowship-of-scholars-in-critical-bibliography-at-rare-book-school&quot;&gt;Sponsor: The Andrew W. Mellon Fellowship of Scholars in Critical Bibliography at Rare Book School&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;organizer-rachel-stein-department-of-latin-american--iberian-cultures-columbia-university-rss2166columbiaedu&quot;&gt;Organizer: Rachel Stein, Department of Latin American &amp;amp; Iberian Cultures, Columbia University (rss2166@columbia.edu)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Symposium “Material Methodologies in Latin American &amp;amp; Iberian Studies” brings together a group of advanced graduate students to share their doctoral research and the diverse ways in which they take materiality into account in their studies of Latin America and the Iberian Peninsula across disciplines. Each participant will give a brief overview of their research project and then perform a reading of one object from their research corpus —whether a textile, printed book, manuscript, or image—from a material perspective. In the presentations and ensuing discussions, we will reflect in particular on the methodological challenges that the study of these Latin American and Iberian objects entails; on the benefits and drawbacks of a material approach; on the particularities and universalities that our regions of study present when considered within the broader field of “Critical Bibliography”; and on the theoretical implications of the work at hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;presentation-abstracts&quot;&gt;Presentation Abstracts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-social-life-of-mantas-native-textiles-and-the-making-of-a-colonial-andean-economy&quot;&gt;The Social Life of Mantas: Native Textiles and the Making of a Colonial Andean Economy&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Santiago Muñoz Arbelaez
Department of History, Yale University&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Muisca peoples who lived in the plateaus in the northern Andes (in present-day Colombia) had a rich textile industry best represented by their mantas––square-formed, hand-painted cloths woven out of cotton. Mantas were relevant in both cultural and economic ways. As culturally significant objects, mantas recorded and transmitted information about social hierarchies and the history of muisca communities. They were part of a broader Andean tradition that blended the acts of weaving, knotting, and drawing as forms of “writing without words,” to use Mignolo and Hill Boone’s terms. Mantas were also central to northern Andean economies prior to the Spanish invasion in 1537. Every year each native chief hosted a great feast in which his subjects gave him white mantas while he gave in return prestigious, hand-painted mantas to high-ranking Indian nobles. After the conquest, mantas became the primary good for colonial tribute and one of the driving forces of the colonial economy under the encomienda system. As a result, encomenderos were challenged with dealing with a product that was foreign to their economic and cultural traditions. My paper follows mantas in their movement across its contexts of production, exchange, and consumption, illustrating some of the ways in which they came in and out of Indian and Spanish spheres in the early colonial world. I argue that the transfer of mantas was crucial in the making of common systems of meaning and exchange between the Muisca and the Spanish in the northern Andes. Because of their peculiar characteristics as Andean and colonial artifacts, mantas offer a novel view of the Spanish colonial economy as a hybrid formation. Since there was no demand for mantas in European markets, Spanish encomenderos often integrated themselves into Indian markets and operated on Muisca economic terms to convert mantas into Spanish forms of wealth. If colonial economic history has generally focused on the gold-seeking attitudes of conquistadors, the economy of mantas allows us to see some of the ways in which encomenderos and other Spaniards were drawn into native economies. As such, it challenges world-systemic approaches that consider South American economies as derived from the needs of the ‘core’ (i. e. Spain), to place native economies at the heart of Spanish colonialism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;a-grammar-for-the-infantas-lullist-instruments-and-pedro-de-guevaras-nueva-y-sutil-invención&quot;&gt;A Grammar for the Infantas: Lullist Instruments and Pedro de Guevara’s Nueva y Sutil Invención&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Noel Blanco Mourelle, PhD Candidate in Latin American &amp;amp; Iberian Cultures, Columbia University&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My intervention will focus on Pedro de Guevara’s Nueva y sutil invención en seis instrumentos (1584) and the way it adapted the fourth figure of the Art of Ramon Llull in order to create a new combinatory method of teaching Latin grammar written in vernacular addressed to king Philip II’s daughters, Isabel and Catalina. I will argue that this method for learning Latin was a single object forming part of a phenomenon I call the early modern portability of Ramon Llull, this is, the transformation and adaptation of the Lullist ideas through their diffusion in book form. Guevara’s Invención coexisted with translations of the Art and more esoteric treatises discussing Lullism during the reign of Philip II. Furthermore, Guevara’s role as preceptor and, thus, supervisor of the education of the infantas Isabel and Catalina shows that Philip II’s Lullism had both public and private implications that the king assumed as a natural part of his interest in the Art. Ultimately, the creation of the instruments in the form of the wheel present in Guevara’s book show the way early modern authors not only received or transmitted a medieval tool, but transformed it through conceptual debate and material alterations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;print-reclaimed-intellectual-history-from-the-printshop-floor-in-nineteenth-century-mexico&quot;&gt;Print Reclaimed: Intellectual History from the Printshop Floor in Nineteenth-Century Mexico&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Corinna Zeltsman, PhD Candidate in History, Duke University&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This presentation focuses on a series of extraordinary type specimens and reports generated in Mexico’s Government Printing Office in the 1870s. Examining the institutional and social context in which these documents were produced and their material and textual qualities, it explores how printers—a group typically assumed to reproduce/re-materialize the words of the powerful through manual labor—both made claims upon superiors and claimed print for themselves. In the process, printers challenged the boundaries between manual and intellectual work and articulated to superiors their own desires for recognition as full participants in the field of knowledge production.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>2019-04-14</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/2015-09/material-methodologies</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/2015-09/material-methodologies</guid>
        
        
        <category>Noticias</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Congreso de la American Historical Association (Atlanta, enero 7-10 de 2016)</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;andean-studies-committee-meeting-the-expanded-andes&quot;&gt;Andean Studies Committee Meeting: The Expanded Andes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;conference-on-latin-american-history&quot;&gt;Conference on Latin American History&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friday, January 8, 2016: 5:00 PM-6:30 PM
International Ballroom A (Atlanta Marriott Marquis, International Level)
Chair:
Jeremy Ravi Mumford, Brown University
Panel:
Nancy P. Appelbaum, Binghamton University (State University of New York)
Santiago Muñoz Arbelaez, Yale University
Cristina Soriano, Villanova University
Comment:
Peter Winn, Tufts University&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>2019-04-14</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/2015-09/american-historical-association</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/2015-09/american-historical-association</guid>
        
        
        <category>Noticias</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Nuevo libro sobre los muiscas y el imperio español</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/costumbres.png&quot; style=&quot;width: 260px; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 10px;&quot; align=&quot;left&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;costumbres-en-disputa-los-muiscas-y-el-imperio-español-en-ubaque-siglo-xvi&quot;&gt;Costumbres en disputa. Los muiscas y el imperio español en Ubaque, siglo XVI&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;bogotá-ediciones-uniandes-2015&quot;&gt;(Bogotá, Ediciones Uniandes, 2015)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.academia.edu/15055353/Costumbres_en_disputa._Los_muiscas_y_el_imperio_espa%C3%B1ol_en_Ubaque_siglo_XVI&quot;&gt;Acá puedes ver y descargar el prefacio&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://libreria.uniandes.edu.co/index.php?page=shop.product_details&amp;amp;flypage=publicaciones&amp;amp;product_id=42980&amp;amp;category_id=9&amp;amp;manufacturer_id=0&amp;amp;option=com_virtuemart&amp;amp;Itemid=26&quot;&gt;Acá lo puedes comprar&lt;/a&gt; (Costo: 35.000 COP; aprox. $11 USD; envío a USA: aprox $19 USD).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;menciÓn-de-honor-premio-nacional-de-historia-2013&quot;&gt;MENCIÓN DE HONOR, PREMIO NACIONAL DE HISTORIA, 2013.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;ministerio-de-cultura--icanh&quot;&gt;MINISTERIO DE CULTURA / ICANH&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;COSTUMBRES EN DISPUTA explora las tensiones que se desataron entre las comunidades muiscas del valle Ubaque con la puesta en marcha del proyecto imperial hispano y muestra cómo las sociedades nativas a la vez respondieron, redimensionaron y resignificaron la dominación colonial. El libro se enfoca en los términos culturales en que se desenvolvieron las relaciones entre los muiscas, los encomenderos y las autoridades coloniales, lo que le permite mostrar otra cara de la encomienda: una en que no sólo los indios tuvieron que responder y ajustarse a las nuevas exigencias coloniales, sino en donde también los encomenderos tuvieron que entender, aceptar e incluso en algunas formas integrarse en las comunidades nativas. El libro argumenta que encomenderos e indígenas forjaron un orden común, aunque asimétrico y a menudo contradictorio, en el contexto de una batalla por las costumbres en la que la manera como se hablaba, vestía o dormía constituía un acto político.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Yanna Yannakakis, Emory University:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Este libro, bellamente escrito, ofrece una nueva perspectiva sobre el colonialismo español en América Latina y más concretamente sobre la encomienda, una institución de importancia central para el período colonial temprano. El sutil análisis re-imagina la cultura colonial como co-construida por los indígenas y los españoles en una lucha permanente sobre las prácticas de la vida cotidiana, incluyendo la sexualidad, el ritual y las relaciones de producción e intercambio. Los nuevos datos y las conclusiones para el caso del valle de Ubaque son cruciales no sólo para nuestra comprensión de la historia de los Andes del norte, sino también para nuestra comprensión del colonialismo en América Latina en términos más generales. Estudiantes y académicos de la sociedad colonial en México y los Andes tendrán mucho que aprender de las comparaciones que provoca este libro.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Joanne Rappaport, Georgetown University:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Muñoz crea un argumento novedoso que expande nuestra comprensión de cómo el cacicazgo cambió en el curso del siglo xvi.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marta Herrera Ángel, Universidad de los Andes:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“En este profundo análisis de uno de los grandes señoríos muisca, el autor evidencia el carácter híbrido de instituciones coloniales como la encomienda. Costumbres en disputa rompe de esta manera con perspectivas que tienden a considerar el orden colonial como una imposición en una sola vía, para entenderlo como un complejo engranaje que incorporó prácticas de diversas culturas.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>2019-04-14</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/articles/2015-08/nuevo-libro-costumbres</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/articles/2015-08/nuevo-libro-costumbres</guid>
        
        
        <category>Noticias</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
